RAHUL VIKAS CHAUDHARI

GIS Analyst

Lane No. 56, Nandpuri colony, Jaipur, Rajasthan-INDIA

Email: mail2r.chaudhari@gmail.com

Phone: 08928968721

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY:

Always seeking for an opportunity to attain a challenging position and to explore the talent in the field of remote sensing and bring forth the best of my creative skills and wealth of knowledge. Diligent experience on Image processing and spatial database customization and modelling with nearly 3 years of experience with Spatial Geodatabases. Enthusiastic, with coordinating and directing to team members in stand-up review meeting.

WORK EXPERIENCE:

Quantum Asia Pvt Ltd.

GIS Analyst

October 2016 to present

- Project working on GIS based watershed planning and monitoring in "Integrated Water Management Program(IWMP)" under nearly 4000 villages and 40.01 lac hectare area get irrigated by watershed inventions within Rajasthan. Currently, posted in Commissionerate, Watershed development and Soil Conservation(WDSC) Department, Jaipur.
- Create, maintain and update GIS layers for watershed modelling.
- Locate potential sites for water harvesting structures using Spatial analysis to identify suitable worksites for "Water Harvesting Structures" under supervision of PSU's Watershed Engineers.
- Review, Correction, and Verification of Spatial layers for Data cleaning and Quality checking.
- Manipulation of Spatial Feature class layer in Geodatabase using Spatial Query and Join.
- Data extraction of specific need for Hydrological Analysis using Conditional statement in Raster Calculator
- Utilized a Spatial Modelling to automate GIS workflows in ESRI Model Builder
- Manipulation and data analysis using Pivot table, pivot charts, Vlookup etc

"JalaSRI", Watershed Surveillance and Research Institute

Associate Researcher

1 October 2015 – 30 August 2016

Project deals with, ICRISAT sponsored project entitled of "Model Watershed Development Programme in-Pathri & Samner Villages of Jalgaon District.

- Automatic delineation of drainage, Watersheds, Drainage ordering, flow accumulation and flow direction using ArcHydro tool
- Extracting a contour lines using DEM in Global Mapper 15.1
- Collection of GCP points and ground water readings of existing well and waterbodies for Hydrological analysis.
- Prepare a Surface and Ground water runoff map using interpolation method
- Prepare impact assessment report of ground water level on the basis of Pre and post analysis
 of hydrological data.

ACADEMIC CREDENTIALS:

MSc in Geoinformatics from Savitribai Phule Pune University, Pune in 2014 (secured 71.52%) BSc in Geoinformatics from Moolji Jaitha College, Jalgaon in 2012 (Secured 75.63%)

TECHNICAL ACHIEVEMENT:

2nd position in Project presentation "Spatial Decision Support System for Transit Route and Public Facilities Management", University level "College Potential Excellence Program 2012" at North Maharashtra University.

KEY ACADEMIC PROJECT

1. Training Project: -

Organization: Department of Geology, Savitribai Phule Pune University, Pune.

Project Tiltle: "Weighted Overlay Analysis for Delineation of Ground Water Potential Zone: A Case Study of

Pirangut River Basin"

Objective: To delineate Ground water potential zone using site suitability analysis.

Description: The continuously decreasing of surface and ground water level produce a scarcity of water resources i.e. imapact on Drinking Water, Irrigation and Industrialization. so, GIS and multicriteria analysis helps to identifying the groundwater potential zones and land suitability for improving agricultural productivity over the area of Pirangut river basin catchments. Assign a ranking method (in between 1-4) with weight for each physical layer for weighted analysis. Data collect from field GCP points and well readings such as depth of GWL, height from MSL helps to perform hypsometry analysis, hydrogeology analysis and Ground Water Flow(GWF).

Softwares: ArcMap, ArcHydro, Surfer, Global Mapper

Duration: December 2013 to May 2014

2. Graduation Project:-

Organization: "JalaSRI", Watershed Surveillance and Research Institute"

Project Title: Spatial Decision Support System for Transit Route and Public Facilities Management

Objective: To finding shortest path between two location and closest utility.

Description: To find shortest distance between two points and closest utility from source point; create and built a city road network dataset with defining connectivity rules and network attributes to display the shortest path. So, it helps to logistic companies and tourist to find nearest path for navigation and utility within a city.

Softwares: ArcCatalog, ArcMap and ArcGIS Network Analyst extension.

Duration: July 2011 to January 2012

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Image processing: ERDAS Imagine 16, Pix4D Mapper
- GIS Software: ArcGIS 10.5, Quantum GIS, Global Mapper 18
- Computer skills: C, C++, Python (beginners level), My SQL, MS Office 2016, Linux
- Others: Surfer, Amazon Web Service(AWS), JEERA, Pivot analysis

EVENT PARTICIPATION & ORGANIZATION

Presented a PPT in College Potential Excellence program on "Spatial Decision Support System for Transit Route And Public Facilities Management" at Moolji Jaitha College, Jalgaon in March 2012

 Attend one-day workshop in Drone fest "DFI 2018" at NMDC Convention Center, New Delhi by Drone Federation of INDIA

PUBLICATIONS

Rahul V. Chaudhari, Dhanesh Lal, Sayantan Dutta, Dr. Bhavna Umrikar, Saheb Halder "WEIGHTED OVERLAY ANALYSIS FOR DELINEATION OF GROUND WATER POTENTIAL ZONE: A CASE STUDY OF PIRANGUT RIVER BASIN", in International Journal of Remote Sensing & Geoscience (January, 2018), Volume 7, Issue 1 (January 2018) pp1-7.

PERSONAL DETAILS

Name : Rahul Vikas Chaudhari Date of Birth : December 29, 1991

Marital Status : Single

Present Address : 55, Lane No. 4, Nandpuri Colony, Jaipur-Rajasthan

Permanent Address : Plot no. 10, Dwarakanagar, Nashirabad, Jalgaon, Maharashtra,

India-425309

Contact Phone: 08928968721 / 08830434186

Email : mail2r.chaudhari@gmail.com

LinkedIN : https://www.linkedin.com/in/rahul-chaudhari-08634278/

REFERENCES

Dr. Mrs. Bhavana Umrikar

Professor,

Hydrogeology, Department of Geology,

Savitribai Phule Pune University, Ganeshkhind, Pune

Email: bnumrikar@gmail.com

DECLARATION

I solemnly declare that all the above information is correct to the best of my knowledge and belief.

Date: 11/07/2019

Place: Jaipur (Rahul Vikas Chaudhari)